<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: websites | ]]></title>
  <link href="/blog/categories/websites/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-12T23:34:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[{"name"=>"Patrick Grey", "email"=>"websemantic@yahoo.co.uk"}]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="https://github.com/recurser/jekyll-plugins">Recurser</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Case Study: PatrickGrey.co.uk]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/case-study/websites/2014/01/11/case-website-patrickgrey.html"/>
    <updated>2014-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>/blog/case-study/websites/2014/01/11/case-website-patrickgrey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I built version 1.0 of this website (you are looking at v2.0) trying to follow the tidal wave of new best practices I had read about over the last couple of years. Once finished, I hated it!</p>

<p>When building v2.0, I tried to rectify many of the mistakes I think I made and I&#39;m actually very happy with the result. I hope you are too!</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/blog/img/2014/jan/2014-01-11-case-website-patrick-grey.jpg" alt="Screenshot of the PatrickGrey.co.uk website." style="max-width:255px;">
  <figcaption>Screenshot of the PatrickGrey.co.uk version 1.0.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In v1.0 I focused too much on trying to get everything to fit in a mobile view without the need to scroll. This was a fundamental flaw. I also loved the idea of using animated SVG (I still do, it just makes sense) but I had to spend a lot of time trying to get it to work cross-browser.</p>

<p>Finally on v1.0, my approach wasn&#39;t structured enough. I was trying to take an overview and implement features to fit into that view. Instead, I should have taken a more task driven approach and focused on each feature at a time.</p>

<p>For v2.0 I took it all back to basics and built it up with very simple aims. The current approach is to add small features to enhance the site as I get time.</p>

<p>I will write some follow-up posts to this one going into more technical detail of how I achieved some aspects of the design.</p>

<h3>Needs Analysis</h3>

<p>My main aim for the site is to help me get work. If a visitor asks, &quot;What can this person do for me?&quot;, I want them to find the answer quickly.</p>

<p>For design and build, I had the following goals:</p>

<ul>
<li>I wanted a clean and clear design and layout.</li>
<li>The site should be responsive</li>
<li>I focused on performance. The site should load very quickly.</li>
<li>It should be quick to build and easy to maintain.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Design</h3>

<p>I started by redesigning my logo. I wanted something to reflect my design approach; clean, balanced colour and a good use of white space. I used the colours in the logo to reflect each section of the site.</p>

<p>I reused the raindrop, which sounds better than drip ;-), motif throughout the rest of the design.</p>

<p>It is a &#39;Flat&#39; design. This appeals to me as it increases the importance of white space and helps cut out design aspects that may impact browser performance (such as large drop shadows).</p>

<p>I tried to keep the text content as minimal as possible. This really focused my mind on what I wanted to say.</p>

<h3>Technical</h3>

<p>The site was scaffolded and tested using  <a href="http://www.Yeoman.io" title="Open the Yeoman.io website in a new window." target="_blank">Yeoman.io</a>, an excellent set of workflow tools.</p>

<p>The pages are created with the <a href="http://jekyllrb.com/" title="Open the jekyllrb.com website in a new window." target="_blank">http://jekyllrb.com/</a> static site generator.</p>

<p>I used the <a href="https://github.com/robwierzbowski/generator-jekyllrb" title="Open the jgenerator-jekyllrb website in a new window." target="_blank">generator-jekyllrb</a> Yeoman generator to get started.</p>

<p>Styles were preprocessed using SASS. Icons and the logo are SVG with a PNG fallback for IE8.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Case Study: JockGordon.co.uk]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/case-study/websites/2014/01/11/case-website-jock-gordon.html"/>
    <updated>2014-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>/blog/case-study/websites/2014/01/11/case-website-jock-gordon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This was a small static site that Jock asked me to build to promote his architectural drawing business on the Island of Skye.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/blog/img/2014/jan/2014-01-11-case-website-jock-gordon.jpg" alt="Screenshot of the JockGordon.co.uk website." style="max-width:700px;">
  <figcaption>Screenshot of the JockGordon.co.uk website.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>You can visit <a href="http://www.jockgordon.co.uk" title="Open the jockgordon.co.uk website in a new window." target="_blank">jockgordon.co.uk here</a>.</p>

<p>Jock wanted a simple site that would require minimal maintenance so I put most of my effort into the visual design. The design aims to reflect the high quality of his designs and emphasize his use of modern materials in an ancient landscape.</p>

<p>It was also important the site would have a high search ranking when people were looking for building design services on Skye. The site has had a top two placing, most commonly first, for a number of years.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&#8220;Patrick couldn&#39;t have been more helpful. He explained everything in a way I could understand and provided lots of advice.
I&#39;m delighted with the site and it has helped my business with a high search engine ranking.&#8221;</p>

<p>Jock Gordon</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Case Study: BarnesTennisClub.co.uk]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/case-study/websites/2014/01/11/case-website-barnes-tennis-club.html"/>
    <updated>2014-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>/blog/case-study/websites/2014/01/11/case-website-barnes-tennis-club</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This was a Wordpress site project for a community tennis club in London.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="/blog/img/2014/jan/2014-01-11-case-website-barnes-tennis.jpg" alt="Screenshot of the BarnesTennisClub.co.uk website." style="max-width:476px;">
  <figcaption>Screenshot of the barnestennisclub.co.uk website viewed on a mobile device.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>You can visit <a href="http://www.barnestennisclub.co.uk" title="Open the BarnesTennisClub.co.uk website in a new window." target="_blank">BarnesTennisClub.co.uk here</a>.</p>

<p>The client wasn&#39;t sure what could be done with a website so I guided them through target audience considerations, the benefits of responsive design and maintenance using a Content Management System. I worked closely with them on the design, social media usage and provided training for the site administrator.</p>

<p>The club has been successfully updating the site themselves since 2012, even creating micro sites aimed at one off events.</p>

<p>The client was so happy with the work, I received a cracking bottle of Oban Malt :-)</p>

<blockquote>
<p>&#8220;We are thrilled with the new look and style...
Thank you for all your time spent on this and I&#39;m sure our Club will prosper as a direct result due to all the new members we will attract.</p>

<p>Best wishes,</p>

<p>Jane Bonner,</p>

<p>Chairman.&#8221;</p>
</blockquote>

<h3>Technical</h3>

<p>I used <a href="http://www.wordpress.org" title="Open the wordpress.org website in a new window." target="_blank">wordpress.org</a> as the Content Management System and the <a href="http://cyberchimps.com/responsive-theme/" title="Open the Cyber Chimps website in a new window." target="_blank">Responsive Theme</a> from Cyber Chimps which I modified with custom CSS and JavaScript.</p>

<p>The theme will work on mobile devices, tablets and desktops.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>