<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: business-time | ]]></title>
  <link href="/blog/categories/business-time/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-23T22:07:34+01:00</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[{"name"=>"Patrick Grey", "email"=>"websemantic@yahoo.co.uk"}]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="https://github.com/recurser/jekyll-plugins">Recurser</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using own name vs business name when self-employed]]></title>
    <link href="/blog/business-time/2013/07/04/own-vs-business-name.html"/>
    <updated>2013-07-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>/blog/business-time/2013/07/04/own-vs-business-name</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been self-employed for about 12 years now, going by the superhero pseudonym of “websemantic”. An AWESOME business name, I’m sure you’ll agree.</p>

<p>I’ve wanted to change it for some time but, to be honest, my business name has had little impact on how I get work. So why change it?</p>

<p>The main confusion I faced when using a &#39;business&#39; name was letting people know what to expect. Am I a company? Do I have staff?
I found myself introducing my site as &#39;websemantic&#39; the business of Patrick Grey etc., just to let people know I was a one man band. It was awkward and unecessary.
So, I can see several benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li>By using my name, people instantly know they are dealing with one person.</li>
<li>Exposure: when I&#39;m online as myself, I&#39;m also spreading recognition of my business.</li>
<li>It&#39;s a better way to build relationships.</li>
<li>I get to play with a new website and branding :-)</li>
</ul>

<p>I did weigh up some possible disadvantages:</p>

<ul>
<li>Confusion as I change name.</li>
<li>As my main business comes from existing relationships, now is an ideal time to change and avoid this.</li>
<li>Potential clients may discount me for work as they presume it will be too large for one person.</li>
<li>A little research would soon show them that I was a sole trader. Hopefully my portfolio will demonstrate the level of work I can deliver.</li>
<li>Hassle: changing details with bank and tax authorities, hosting, stationary, email etc.</li>
<li>Changing my digital profile is part of my job and was actually quite interesting to do. It was a good chance to tidy up and clean my &#39;workspace&#39;. HMRC and bank? I don&#39;t think they are too bothered but I will let them know and see how easy it is to change. Not much effort I suspect.</li>
<li>I lose a relatively high Google ranking.</li>
<li>Part of the job to get the new domain back up the listings and perhaps improve it for different search keywords.</li>
</ul>

<p>Overall, I like the idea of having a refresh of my business. I can tidy things up and use the rebranding to try out new things. A new lick of paint gave me that excitiment I had when I started the business!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>